Guide to the Meyer Schapiro letters and manuscripts of Whittaker Chambers and James Thomas Farrell
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Meyer Schapiro Letters and Manuscripts of Whittaker Chambers and James Thomas Farrel,
1923-1991.
Schapiro, Meyer, 1904-1996.
3 linear ft. (ca. 1,250 items in 6 boxes)
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027
4079304
Biographical Note
Educator, art critic, and professor of fine arts at Columbia University, 1928-1965, University Professor, 1965-1973, Prof. Schapiro (Columbia Univ BA, 1924; MA 1926, Ph.D., 1929) died in 1996.
Scope and Content
Autograph and typed letters from James Thomas Farrell to Schapiro, concerning Farrell's personal life, his writings, and current social and political affairs. There are also eight of Farrell's manuscripts from the 1960s. The long friendship of neighbors is seen in Farrell's personal letters about his private life and his family and in the discussions of whichever novel he was working on at the time. The main body of the correspondence is from the World War II period and shows much concern for current events in the Soviet Union as well as in the U.S. and Europe. The author also made a few forays into Irish humor, as in the use of his pseudonym, Jonathan Titelescu Fogarty. There are autograph drafts of Prof. Schapiro's replies to and notes about Farrell, and letters and post cards from Farrell's actress wife, Hortense Adler. Also, a letter from Frances Mitchell on her book, The Awakening - Le Revile, 1950.
1995 Addition: 70 letters from Whittaker Chambers to Meyer Schapiro, along with copies of his letters and research material about Chambers.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 5 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Ccataloged Manuscripts
Series III: Clippings
Series IV: Miscellaneous Material
Series V: Research Materials on Whittaker Chambers
Subjects
Columbia University--Faculty.; United States.--Federal Bureau of Investigation.; Adler, Hortense.; Buckley, William F. (William Frank), 1925-2008.; Chambers, Whittaker.; Corman, Cid.; Farrell, James T. (James Thomas), 1904-1979.; Hiss, Alger.; Mitchell, Frances, 1914-; Anti--ommunist movements--United States.; Communism--United States--20th century.; Irish wit and humor.; Subversive activities--United States--20th century.; World War, 1939-1945--Europe.; World War, 1939-1945--Soviet Union.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; Affidavits.; Articles.; Depositions.; Invitations.; Memorandums.; Notes.; Poems.; Releases.; Reviews.; Transcripts.; Subpoenas.; Actresses.; Authors, American--20th century.; College teachers.; Journalists.; Spies.; Women authors.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1982 M-82 Schapiro, Meyer Gift
02/08/1995 M-02-08-95 W.Chambers material Schapiro, Meyer Gift
10/25/1996 M-96-10-25 Papers Schapiro, Meyer Bequest
Gift of Meyer Schapiro, 1982, 1984, & 1995.
Bequest of Meyer Schapiro, 1996.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Buckley, William Frank, Jr., 1925- To Meyer Schapiro, Switz., 24 Feb. 1967, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 1)
    [Signed by Secretary; with copy of related letters]
  - Chambers, Whittaker, 1901-1961 To Meyer Schapiro, [v.p.], [1924-1953], (44 a.l.s., 1 a.l., 9 t.l.s., 18 t.l., 2 a.p.c.s., 1 p.l.) (Box 1)
    [Reading copies]
  - Chambers, Whittaker To the Politburo of the Communist Party USA, [n.p.], [Early 1937], (1 ms.l.) (Box 1)
    [Reading Copies; "Dictated by WC," in the hand of Meyer Schapiro?; 2 photocopies and 1 typewritten transcript]
  - Chiaromonte, Nicola To Meyer Schapiro, [New York?], 2 Aug & [summer] 1944, (1 a.l.s., 1 t.l.s.) (Box 2)
  - Corman, Cid To Meyer Schapiro, Kyoto, 25 July 1983, (2 t.l.s.) (Box 2)
  - Farrell, Hortense Alden (Mrs. James T.) To Meyer Schapiro, v.p., [1938] - 1944, (5 t.l.s.) (Box 2)
  - Farrell, Hortense Alden (Mrs. James T.) To Mr. and Mrs. Meyer Schapiro, Rheims & Chartres, July [ca.l] - 8, 1938, (2 a.p.c.s.) (Box 2)
    [Signed by "Hortense and Jim"]
  - Farrell, James T. To Meyer Schapiro, [v.p.], 11 Dec 1937 - 29 May 1944, (389 t.l.s., 69 t.l., 3 a.p.c.s., 25 a.l.s., 1 t.pc.) (Box 2)
  - Farrell, James T. To Meyer Schapiro, [v.p.], 2 June 1944 - 24 Aug 1974, (257 t.l.s., 24 t.l., 2 a.p.c.s., 174 a.l.s.) (Box 3)
  - Farrell, James T. To Meyer Schapiro, [v.p.], 5 Feb 1976 - 1 June 1979, (86 t.l.s., 3 t.l., 3 t.p.c.s., 6 a.l.s.) (Box 4)
  - Mitchell, Frances To Meyer Schapiro, New York, [ca. 1950], (2 t.l.s.) (Box 4)
  - Schapiro, Meyer To James T. Farrell, [New York], [June - July 1938?], (1 t.l.) (Box 4)
    [With 3-page draft in the author's hand]
- Series II: Ccataloged Manuscripts
  - Farrell, James T. "Author defends character Studs Lonigan", Louisville, 22 Nov 1960, (2 t.ms.) (Box 5)
    [Multilith copy: "Comment by Farrell" as printed in The Louisville Times ]
  - Farrell, James T. "The action of the government of Irag...", [New York], 6 Feb 1969, (5 t.ms.) (Box 5)
    [Carbon copy: With corrections in the writer's hand; article for a journal; with envelope]
  - Farrell, James T. Golden Youth, [New York], 1963, (3 a.ms.) (Box 5)
    [Poem; with covering a.n.]
  - Farrell, James T. John Fitzgerald Kennedy, [New York], 1963, (1 a.ms.) (Box 5)
    [Poem; autograph note indicates the poem was printed in the Congressional Record, 15 Jan 1964]
  - Farrell, James T. Lebanon: a first impression, [New York], 1961, (7 t.ms.) (Box 5)
    [Essay on the political situation in the Middle East; "unpublished"]
  - Farrell, James T. Political Parties...by Robert Michels, New York, [1966-67], (7 t.ms.) (Box 5)
    [xerox copy; article on Michels' book, suggested by J.P. Nettl's biography of Rosa Luxemburg, Oxford University Press, 1966]
  - Farrell, James T. Requiem For a Literary Bank Account, [New York], [1961?], (4 t.ms.s) (Box 5)
    [p.4 missing; multilith copy, title and notes in the author's hand, with his signature]
  - Farrell, James T. What Time Collects, [New York], [Feb 1964], (15 t.ms.) (Box 5)
    [Final draft of Chapters thirty-three, thirty-four, and thirty-six]
  - Schapiro, Meyer [Comments on James T. Farrell's achievements], [S. Londonderry, Vt.], 9 Aug 1978, (1 t.ms.) (Box 5)
    [Commendation on James T. Farrell in reply to the request of the University of Chicago Alumni Association in considering him for their Professional Achievement Award.]
  - Raphael, Max Zur Erkenntnistheorie des Marxismus, [Paris], [1933], (280 t.ms.) (Box 5)
    [the last 10 pages: Anmerkungen]
- Series III: Clippings
  - Farrell, James T. Clippings about... (Box 5)
- Series IV: Miscellaneous Material
  - Farrell, James T. Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 5)
  - Farrell, James T. Miscellaneous letters about (Box 5)
  - Farrell, James T. printed articles (Box 5)
  - Notes removed from Ammianus Marcellinus, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Notes removed from "Hero of Alexandria", 1996 (Box 5)
  - Notes removed from "Oracula Sibyllina", 1996 (Box 5)
- Series V: Research Materials on Whittaker Chambers
  - Tanenhaus, 1995 (Box 6)
  - Herbert Solow, 1995 (Box 6)
  - Clippings, 1995 (Box 6)
  - Clippings, articles, etc., 1995 (Box 6)
  - Poems, 1922-25, from the Zukovsky Papers, Univ. of Texas (Austin), 1995 (Box 6)
  - cleared; ready for CU, 1995 (Box 6)
  - VIII, 1995 (Box 6)
  - IX, 1995 (Box 6)
  - X: Hamilton, J.W., 1978-80, 1995 (Box 6)
  - Allen Weinstein, 1975, 1995 (Box 6)
  - XII, 1995 (Box 6)
  - Notes for J.D. Fox, 1995 (Box 6)